Okay בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is י"ד. Yud Dalet.
We're a little behind. We start on the משנה Mishna on ג
ו-ב, Gimmel Vav Bet, a new משנה, Mishna, a new discussion. ואלו
מן ההלכות שאמרו בעליית חנניה בן חזקיה בן גרון V’elu min hahalachot
she’amru ba’aliyat Chananya ben Chizkiyah ben Garon שעלו לבקרו. she’alu l’vakro. These
are from the הלכות halachot that they said in the store in
the attic or the whatever the second story of חנניה בן חזקיה
בן גרון Chananya ben Chizkiyah ben Garon that when they went to
visit him. נמנו ורבו בית שמאי על בית הלל, Nimnu v’rabu Beit
Shammai al Beit Hillel, so there was a majority of בית שמאי
Beit Shammai outmembered בית הלל, Beit Hillel, so they realized that they
finally had the majority, so they figured what a perfect time to
pass some legislation that's been caught up in committee. ואיתכס דבר ואסקוהו
ביומא V’itchas davar v’askuhu b’yoma and they managed through and they managed.
So we're going to see.
That's what I was going to ask.
All right. Okay, everybody. So it's here because what we've just taught
or as more what we're about to teach is from those הלכות.
halachot. So therefore it says you should be aware that these things
we taught about not going out with the pin in your the
tailor carrying his pin or the scribe carrying his feather or a
זב zav and a זבה zavah not eating together, maybe not sitting
down before מנחה Mincha time, all of these type all of these
were from the י"ח דבר, Yud Chet Davar, the 18 things that
they decided in the attic of חנניה בן גרון. Chananya ben Garon.
So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. Little historical footnote. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, Amar lei
Abaye l’Rav Yosef, so אביי Abaye says to רב יוסף: Rav Yosef:
אלו תנן או ואלו תנן? Elu tnan o v’elu tnan?
These or and these? What difference does it make? ואלו תנן הני
דאמרין. V’elu tnan hani d’amrin. If it's ואלו, v’elu, then it's connected
to what we said before. So it means those that we just
listed above are amongst these הלכות halachot of the י"ח דבר, Yud
Chet Davar, the 18 things. או דילמא אלו תנן, O dilma elu
tnan, the following are, these that we will say דבעינא למימר קמן
d’ba’ina l’meimar kaman or about to say. So ואלו v’elu connects it
to the earlier discussion, אלו elu opens up a new discussion. So
which משנה, Mishna, which משניות mishnayot are from amongst those things taught
from בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, בית הלל? Beit Hillel? תא שמע, Ta
shema, come and hear. אין פולין לאור הנר ואין קורין לאור הנר
ואלו מן ההלכות שאמרו בעליית חנניה בן חזקיה בן גרון. Ein polin
l’or haner v’ein korin l’or haner v’elu min hahalachot she’amru ba’aliyat Chananya
ben Chizkiyah ben Garon. So a similar ברייתא, braita, but there's no
but it ends with that. There's no nothing afterwards that it could
be confused of which whether it's referring to previous or following. It
only has that one unit. שמע מינה, Shma mina, ואלו תנן שמע
מינה, v’elu tnan shma mina, you see it's going on what we
taught before. So now you have some of the earlier משניות mishnayot
are from this teaching. It's not clear how far back that goes.
Presumably it certainly goes back to the issues about the שבת Shabbat
and reading לאור הנר l’or haner and so on. It was clear
by the way that reading לאור הנר l’or haner was an ancient
was a very early תקנה takanah because if you remember רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael who was relatively early said I was once reading לאור
הנר l’or haner and I almost tipped the candle and I see
that the sages were right when they said אין קורין לאור הנר.
ein korin l’or haner. So certainly it seems like the going out
with the quill or the reading לאור הנר l’or haner and the
זב zav and זבה zavah eating together, presumably all of that is
from those 18 things. Does it go so far back to also
include not sitting down to the barber before מנחה? Mincha? Maybe. The
רמב"ם Rambam actually tries to extend it all the way back to
the first משנה Mishna about the עני ani and the בעל הבית.
baal habayit. And that's and the רמב"ם Rambam has a way of
counting that he gets basically up to 18 because by the עני
ani and the בעל הבית, baal habayit, remember it's two which are
four inside, two which are four outside, that's eight. And then he
gets about five from the things you're not supposed to do before
מנחה Mincha time, barber, bathhouse, all these other things. And then he
gets five from the things you're not supposed to carry right before
שבת Shabbat and that reading לאור הנר, l’or haner, and the רמב"ם
Rambam gets 18 out of all the previous three משניות. mishnayot. That's
generally not assumed to be the case. It's assumed to be that
the משנה Mishna that started with carrying, maybe the משנה Mishna of
sitting down before מנחה, Mincha, and מן ההלכות, min hahalachot, it's a
selection, these are some of the things that were taught, but it
is not the complete list. So it is an abbreviated list.
Okay, this thing you'd think you'd have like a whole list of
something that's important.
All right, but a lot of these have to do with טומאה
וטהרה tumah v’taharah and thankfully רבי Rebbi didn't want to get us
into that. The גמרא Gemara will, of course. Okay, let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, so rabbis taught:
מי כתב מגילת תענית? Mi katav Megillat Taanit? Who wrote מגילת תענית?
Megillat Taanit? Oh, I meant to bring it in. I'm sorry. מגילת
תענית Megillat Taanit is, I mean, I don't have the actual original
מגילה, megillah, but it's there's a nice academic versions of this out
there. It's a very ancient text and one that actually was written
even in an oral culture, which is unusual. One of the reasons
maybe it was written is because it was just a lot of
dates and it was hard to remember all of the dates. Not
exactly clear why that but whatever it was, it was written down.
And there actually it lists the dates that you're not allowed to
have a fast on and you're not allowed to have a הספד
hesped on. So it's sort of a מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit because
it's by if you're making fast days, you need to consult this
list to make sure you're not doing it on any of the
following days. And there are a lot of minor little holidays, things
that were like historically significant at the time that we don't keep.
But interestingly, the whole חנוכה Chanukah is from מגילת תענית, Megillat Taanit,
like
the
early... which is also contemporaneous but in terms of the Rabbinic institution
of חנוכה, Chanukah, the earliest source is that מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit
because it describes what happened on those days that you're not supposed
to fast. Okay, so who wrote this book? So מי כתב מגילת
תענית? Mi katav Megillat Taanit? אמרו Amru they said חנניה בן חזקיה
וסיעתו, Chananya ben Chizkia v’siato, חנניה בן חזקיה Chananya ben Chizkia and
his colleagues שהיו מחבבים
את הצרות she’hayu mechabevim et ha’tsarot that they would they found the
afflictions very dear. Now, you take that on its surface meaning, it
means that and look, there are theologies like this, right? Suffering brings
atonement, if we're being punished it's ultimately and maybe it's not only
the way we've suffered in the past but maybe through inflicting suffering
upon ourselves it brings כפרה kapara so maybe it's a type of
a people, look, we know חסידי אשכנז, Chassidei Ashkenaz, you know, in
the eleventh tenth eleventh twelfth century whatever, you know, major part of
their religious experience was about self-flagellation and imposing you know imposing you
know self-denial and so on. So read that way, the point is
is that that these this is a group of people that are
looking for every opportunity to fast. So in general fasting is a
major part of their religious lives and but therefore they have to
write a מגילה Megilla to at least indicate which days they're not
allowed to fast. Most of us we wouldn't even think about fasting
except the five times we're supposed to fast or whatever so who
needs a מגילת תענית? Megillat Taanit? But if you're looking to fast
all the time then you need a מגילת תענית. Megillat Taanit. רש"י
Rashi does not read it that way. רש"י Rashi says מחבבים את
הצרות mechabevim et ha’tsarot meaning they were מחבב mechabev the days when
their צרה tsara was imminent and God saved them. I understand and
that's why they wrote מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit to be a record
of all of those minor miracles and all of those, you know,
celebratory days that something good had happened and therefore they shouldn't fast.
But it's again the simple language speaks about the צר, tsar, not
being saved from the צר. tsar. אמר רבן גמליאל Amar Rabban Gamliel
אף אנו מחבבים את הצרות. af anu mechabevim et ha’tsarot. We also,
you know, find dear the צרות. tsarot. אבל מה נעשה Aval ma
na’aseh שאם באנו לכתוב אין אנו מספיקין. she’im banu lichtov ein anu
maspikin. But if what do we want to do because if we
were to write it down we would not have we wouldn't it
wouldn't we wouldn't be able to write it all down. Now, according
to the way I read just the פשט, pshat, it's very straightforward.
It says, look, we also get a lot of affliction suffering, you
know, from our friends the Romans these days and all these types
of things. But, you know, we're not we can't go ahead and
identify all of the types of all of them, there's אין סוף.
ein sof. Of course the problem here is and this is why
רש"י Rashi explains it differently is that what was written אם באנו
לכתוב im banu lichtov if we were to write it down which
was what was written was not sort of the צרות tsarot which
was written was the salvations from the צרות. tsarot. So רש"י Rashi
has to sort of reverse this so if you I'll read you
רש"י, Rashi, he says wait minute אין אנו
מספיקין
ein anu
maspikin לפי
שהן אין אנו מספיקין לעשות יום טוב בכל יום. ein anu maspikin
la’asot yom tov be’chol yom. So רש"י Rashi says, ah, we also
are saved every single day from צרות. tsarot. So I guess if
you're constantly viewing I mean in a way it is the flip
side of constantly being oppressed. If you're constantly being oppressed then God
willing there are also a lot of little miracles along the way,
right? There's a lot of times when there was almost a pogrom
and something happened, almost this happened, you know, almost something terrible happened
so if you're living in an oppressed state you can understand how
you could also see a lot more miracles, right? We're living in
a very, you know, good life where we can trust on health
and food and all these types of things so we don't see
miracles. We just see, you know, we have it good.
But we do and there's one they terror attacks thwarted.
Right, right, that's true but you know we should be able to
see miracles in our day-to-day prosperity. We do!
Some people do, Bobby. I'm saying ברוך השם Baruch Hashem that you
do but sadly it's
so many people, I'm not just Bobby.
All right, I know but I think so thank you that's true
but sadly a lot of people when everything is going good it's
harder for them to see than when things are bad or things
are imminent bad things happen and then they're saved from it. So
that's how I would read according to רש"י Rashi what he's saying.
He's saying we also have a lot of צרות tsarot and because
we have a lot of צרות tsarot we also see a lot
of times where we're saved from those צרות tsarot and therefore but
we can't write all of them down yes.
At what time in history did he write this did רש"י Rashi
write this commentary? Was it before after the first crusade?
Yeah, I don't know but he is talking historically about right about
what was going on in the גמרא Gemara but I don't know.
All right so the גמרא Gemara says
I mean he revised his פירוש peirush many times. Okay. דבר אחר
אין שוטה נפגע. Davar acher ein shoteh nifga.
Somebody who is a שוטה shoteh is not aware about you know
sort of like not of right mind doesn't know when he's being
smitten doesn't know when he's being hurt. ודבר אחר אין בשר המת
מרגיש באיזמל. Ve’davar acher ein basar ha’met margish be’izmel.
A dead flesh doesn't feel like the piercing of an awl. So
what does that mean?
So רש"י Rashi says you know אין פגע בא בה ein pega
ba ba לומר אין מכה בפגע lomar ein maka be’fega כך כמה
נסים באים לנו ואין אנו מכירים בהם. kach kama nissim ba’im lanu
v’ein anu makirim ba’hem.
So here also like we are not aware of all of the
miracles that have you know all of the... possible things that could
have happened to us that did not happen to us. So again,
if you're living in a time of of oppression,
you see threats constantly. On the one hand you might be you
might see a lot of days of God's intervention and therefore we
can't list all those days. Or the flip is it is so
much a constant threat that we're not even aware of how many
times God has been intervening behind the scenes and certain things said
not happen. And that's the idea of אין שוטה נפגע ein shoteh
nifga we're unaware as you know we're בשר המת. basar hamet. But
you know the בשר המת basar hamet and the שוטה shoteh also
also give an image of like we've become inured to them. You
know, we've have so constant that we've become inured to the you
know to the affliction. And if you read again back to the
פשט pshat that it's not about רש״י Rashi but about the גאולה,
geulah, about feeling the affliction, then I think you understand the metaphor
much better. You know, that if you are constantly being afflicted after
a certain point you say, you know, you no longer have you
know appreciate how bad you have it because it's become the new
normal. So, so again it's a question whether he's emphasizing all the
goods that we're not aware of or all of the bad that
we become a little inured to. Okay, anyway, now the גמרא Gemara
digresses a little. Is this really true that dead flesh cannot feel
an awl? האמר רב יצחק ha'amar Rav Yitzchak קשה רימה למת כמחט
בבשר החי. kasheh rimah lamet kemachat bivsar hachai.
The maggot when it eats the dead body, it affects the the
dead person, their spirit, the same way a needle would hurt you
if you were to pierce it from of a live person. שנאמר
shene'emar אך בשרו עליו יכאב ונפשו עליו תאבל. ach besaro alav yichav
v'nafsho alav te'eval. His flesh will cause be painful to him when
he's dead. So you see that that things do hurt the dead.
אימא אין בשר המת שבחיים מרגיש באזמל. eima ein basar hamet shebachayim
margish b'izmel. Okay, it doesn't mean the flesh of a dead person;
somehow the spirit is affected there. What it means is that for
a live person who has a portion of his flesh which is
dead, there it won't hurt. Like if you have a callus. That's
what a callus is; it's dead skin to protect your skin, right?
So if you would pierce your callus with a needle, you wouldn't
feel it because it's dead. There's no nerve endings. Okay. Or your
fingernails. Or your fingernails, right. That's not
dead
skin
but
right. Okay. So, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav ברם זכור אותו איש לטוב, beram zachur oto ish letov, that
person should be remembered for good, וחנניה בן חזקיה שמו, v'Chananya ben
Chizkiyah shemo, שאלמלא הוא נגנז ספר יחזקאל. she'ilmala hu nignaz Sefer Yechezkel.
Another thing that he did in with it is that were not
for him, he would have they would have had to hide away,
meaning not canonize, the book of יחזקאל. Yechezkel. It would have had
to have been a you know a ספר חיצוני Sefer Chitzoni essentially,
a non-recognized book. Why? שהיו דבריו סותרים דברי תורה. shehayu devarav sotrim
divrei Torah. Because at the פשט pshat of the book of יחזקאל
Yechezkel there's a lot of things that contradict. It's true. And in
יחזקאל Yechezkel it says like for example, רש״י Rashi quotes one example.
It says there, it says like that כהנים kohanim should not eat
נבלה. neveilah. So it sounds like כהנים kohanim shouldn't eat נבלה; neveilah;
other people can eat נבלה. neveilah. So there's a lot of things
in יחזקאל, Yechezkel, the way it describes the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
is very different, although maybe it's הבית השלישי, haBayit HaShlishi, but a
lot of הלכות halachot even in פסוקים psukim in יחזקאל Yechezkel which
are against the תורה. Torah. So what are we going to do?
So there was a desire not to canonize it. מה עשה? mah
asah? What did he do? העלו לו ג׳ מאות גרבי שמן. he'elu
lo gimmel meot garvei shemen. He brought up 300, whatever, barrels or
something of oil, וישב בעלייה ודרשן. v'yashav ba'aliyah v'darshan.
And they they sat in his attic, him and presumably him and
a group of רבנים, rabbanim, and they found ways to reconcile. Why
they need the attic? Because they're going oil, they're going late into
the night. רש״י Rashi says they also needed the food. Anyway, they
locked themselves in a room for for three months and they solved
all the problems, they come up with ways to reconcile. So the
interesting thing about these two stories about חנניה בן גרון Chananya ben
Geron is that he is you know he's very involved first of
all in scripture-related stuff: יחזקאל, Yechezkel, writing a new מגילה, megillah, מגילת
תענית. Megillat Ta'anit. When you say the word מגילה megillah for us
it has sort of religious resonance. Not so clear that it did
for them but whatever. But very much about sort of written things
that are important for religious our religious lives. And that he did
it with a group of רבנים. rabbanim. He brought maybe he was
wealthy; he was able to support these these endeavors and he brought
everybody there to discuss. So the רמב״ם Rambam says, not unrealistically, that
it was during one of these meetings—he says about the יחזקאל Yechezkel
but could have been about the מגילת תענית—that Megillat Ta'anit the event
of our משנה Mishnah took
place, that they said that בית שמאי Beit Shammai outnumbers בית הלל,
Beit Hillel, let's do some other business while we're here. Let's take
care of some other stuff and they passed the יח דברים yud-chet
devarim in the when they were doing these issues. Okay. Yes, Bobby?
One little aside.
Yes. A fingernail is produced by living skin cells in the finger
and I won't go into the rest of it. Okay, fine.
Okay.
Okay. Point well taken. Now moving on to the 18 things: ושמונה
עשר דבר גזרו. u'shmonah asar davar gazru. 18 things they decided when
they were with חנניה בן גרון. Chananya ben Geron. Let's take a
look.
I'm sorry, חזקיה בן גרון. Chizkiyah ben Geron.
I jumped a generation.
Yeah,
what's the significance of the
attic?
I don't know. That's just where it was. Maybe that was where
he had his like his big meeting room. That he lived on
the bottom floor and upstairs is where they had like a I'm
serious they had a huge room where all the rabbis could gather.
but it seems like the second story was used for some large
meeting room.
Yeah, it plays a role in the New Testament as well, the
idea of an upper room.
Really? Interesting. Okay.
Like separating and yeah.
Right. Okay, it could have been like, you know, they went down
to the basement where they had their rec room and they all
sat there. Okay, for שמונה עשר דבר גזרו Shmonah Asar Davar Gazru
they had eighteen things they passed. מאי נינהו Mai ninhu what are
they?
שמונה עשר דבר. Shmonah Asar Davar. דתנן Detnan אלו פוסלין את התרומה.
Eilu Poslin et ha-Trumah. The following things invalidate תרומה, Trumah, meaning that
are considered a שני sheni and only תרומה Trumah can become a
שלישי. shlishi. So the following things are a שני לטומאה sheni l'tumah
that they would make תרומה Trumah שלישי shlishi פוסל posel because then
the תרומה Trumah would not be able to pass it on, it
ends there. What are these things? האוכל אוכל ראשון והאוכל אוכל שני.
Ha-ochel ochel rishon v'ha-ochel ochel sheni. If somebody eats food that is
a ראשון rishon or food that's a שני, sheni, food that touched
an אב הטומאה Av ha-Tumah like a שרץ, sheretz, or food that's
a שני sheni like food touched a vessel that touched an אב
הטומאה, Av ha-Tumah, so it's second-degree derivative. All those types of things,
if you were to touch it you should be נטמא nitma because
a person can only become a ראשון. rishon. So if you were
to touch a ראשון rishon you should be נטמא. nitma. A שני
sheni נטמא. nitma. A person can only become טמא tamei by touching
an אב. av. Nevertheless, one of the things they said is, if
you eat the food that's a ראשון rishon or שני, sheni, then
you become a שני. sheni. And therefore now if you touch תרומה
Trumah you'll make it פסול. pasul.
So if you eat a ראשון rishon you're a שני, sheni, you
eat a שני sheni you're also a שני? sheni?
Yes. We'll take, we'll see, don't worry, we're going to deal with
all these. והשותה משקין טמאים V'hashoteh mashkin t'meirim if you drink liquid
that's טמא tamei either a ראשון rishon or a שני, sheni, although
liquid really can't be a שני, sheni, which is why it doesn't
distinguish, liquid basically automatically upgrades to a ראשון. rishon. So also you
become a
שני. sheni. והבא ראשו ורובו במים שאובים V'haba rosho v'rubo b'mayim she'uvim
if you basically take a bath, your head and most of your
body goes into drawn water, you become a שני. sheni. That's number
four. וטהור שנפלו על ראשו ורובו שלשה לוגין מים שאובים V'tahor she'naflu
al rosho v'rubo shlosha lugin mayim she'uvim or you take a shower,
a טהור tahor person that three לוג log of drawn water, which
is what is three לוג? log? It's about nine liters.
Okay, is that why?
I don't know, is that what it says? A לוג log is
a לוג log is about fourteen ounces, so about I don't know,
forty-two, forty-something ounces or something, whatever that works out to. Anyway, a
drawn water falls on you, you take a shower, that's number, we're
up to five I
think. והספר והידיים. V'ha-Sefer v'ha-Yadayim. Wait, so what happens if you do?
You
become, all these you become a שני. sheni. Okay. והספר והידיים V'ha-Sefer
v'ha-Yadayim if you touch ספרי קודש Sifrei Kodesh like a ספר תורה
Sefer Torah or other types of books of the תנ"ך, Tanakh, you
become a, they are, excuse me, they themselves are a שני. sheni.
ספרי קודש Sifrei Kodesh are שני, sheni, have טומאה, tumah, which is
interesting. ידיים, Yadayim, your hands are always considered to be a שני
sheni even if just as a general rule, which is why we
wash our hands before we eat bread, because bread sort of evokes
the idea of כהנים kohanim eating תרומה. Trumah. So if your hands
are always a שני, sheni, כהנים kohanim would always have to wash
their hands before they ate bread. Now we should say that in
addition to the fact that this is all a new rabbinic thing
that allows a person to be a שני, sheni, and like I
said a person really can only be a ראשון, rishon, it's also
a very big rabbinic new rabbinic invention that only your hands can
be טמא tamei without the rest of your body. According to הלכה
halakha you're all טמא tamei or you're all טהור. tahor. Okay, but
here we treat the hands always as a שני. sheni. I think
we're up to seven. והטבול יום V'hatvul Yom somebody who's gone to
the מקווה mikvah that day before sunset is a שני sheni and
will make תרומה טמא. terumah tamei. That's eight. Although the גמרא Gemara
will exclude טבול יום tvul yom because that's דאורייתא. de'oraita. So it's
just being thrown in here amongst the list of things that are
a שני, sheni, but it's not amongst the eighteen things that בית
שמאי ובית הלל Beit Shammai v'Beit Hillel agreed upon. והאוכלים והכלים שנטמאו
במשקין V'ha-ochlin v'ha-keilim she'nitme'u b'mashkin
foods and vessels that became טמא tamei. through liquid. So even though
vessels first of all should not be able to be a שני,
sheni, and food can be a שני sheni but sometimes it won't
let's say, nevertheless we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, these also always
become a שני. sheni. So that's nine. והאוכלים והכלים שנטמאו במשקין V'ha-ochlin
v'ha-keilim she'nitme'u b'mashkin
right, foods and liquids that became...
foods and vessels excuse me, that became טמא tamei with liquids. Okay,
so now
that's not all eighteen. But that is what?
We have the ones from before
like אין פולין ואין קורין. Ein polin v'ein korin. Right. So anyway
these are from then. Okay, but at least we'll, the גמרא Gemara
will know, the גמרא's Gemara going to add, the גמרא Gemara will
complete the list. But we're starting the list with this משנה Mishnah
in זבים, Zavim, which is about nine different ways of things being
a שני. sheni. So a lot of these eighteen things had to
do with טומאה וטהרה. Tumah v'Taharah. A lot of בית שמאי ובית
הלל Beit Shammai v'Beit Hillel sort of has to do with טומאה
וטהרה. Tumah v'Taharah. A lot of their earlier, earliest concerns which again
shows the sort of prevalence of the whole, you know, focus of
the religious importance of טומאה וטהרה Tumah v'Taharah even after the חורבן.
Churban. Okay, so now let's go ahead and unpack this. So the
of these things. So מאן תנא אוכל אוכל ראשון ואוכל אוכל שני
מפסל פסלי טמויי לא מטמו. Man tana ochel ochel rishon v'ochel ochel
sheni mifsil pasli t'muyei lo mtamyei. Who is the one that said
that these things if you eat a ראשון rishon or a שני
sheni you become פסול, pasul, you become a שני sheni
but you do not make, you're not טמא. tamei טמא tamei. means
you would be a ראשון, rishon, you would be able to make
something טמא Tamei and it makes something else טמא. tamei So who
says So when you eat these foods, you become a שני sheni
and not a ראשון. rishon. Top of דף י״ד עמוד א׳. Daf
Yud Dalet Amud Alef. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יהושע
היא. Amar Rabbah Bar Bar Channah Amar Rabbi Yehoshua hi. It’s רבי
יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. דתנן, Detnan, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer Omer, האוכל
אוכל ראשון ראשון, ha-ochel ochel rishon rishon, ואוכל אוכל שני שני. ve-ochel
ochel sheni sheni. So this is what Michael would have more wanted
to say. Maybe there’s a difference. If you eat a ראשון, rishon,
you become what you were, a ראשון. rishon. You are what you
eat. If you eat a שני, sheni, you become a שני. sheni.
So at least there are ways that you could eat food and
be a ראשון. rishon. If you ate food that was a ראשון,
rishon, food that touched a שרץ, sheretz, you eat it, so you
become as if you touched the שרץ, sheretz, you become a ראשון.
rishon. That’s the first opinion.
That’s what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says. אוכל שלישי שלישי, ochel shlishi
shlishi, and if you eat food that’s a שלישי, shlishi, which can
only be תרומה, Trumah then you become a שלישי, shlishi, which means
the only relevance is if you touch קודש. kodesh. רבי יהושע אומר,
Rabbi Yehoshua Omer, האוכל אוכל ראשון ואוכל אוכל שני שני. ha-ochel ochel
rishon ve-ochel ochel sheni sheni.
Note, whether you ate a ראשון rishon or a שני, sheni, you’re
a שני. sheni. What happens by eating טמא tamei. food is you
become a שני. sheni. ושלישי, ve-shlishi, and if you ate food that’s
a שלישי, shlishi, then שני לקודש ואין שני לתרומה, sheni le-kodesh ve-ein
sheni le-trumah, בחולין שנעשו על טהרת תרומה. be-chullin she-na’asu al taharat trumah.
So then you become a שני sheni vis-a-vis קודש. kodesh. If you
touch something that’s קודש, kodesh, you become a שני. sheni.
Let me just one second, I just want to check one thing
in רש״י. Rashi.
Right. And but you do not become a, but you are not
a שני sheni vis-a-vis תרומה. trumah, And even this that we are
saying that if you eat a שלישי shlishi you become טמא tamei
is only when what became a שלישי? shlishi? חולין chullin that was
treated as if it was תרומה. trumah. Meaning one of the הלכות
halachot is that if you treat certain food, if you’re מקפיד makpid
to always, one thing is you’re מקפיד makpid to always your חולין
בטהרה. chullin be-taharah. Even when you’re eating non-תרומה, trumah. you’ll be טהור.
tahor. But another level is not only am I מקפיד makpid my
חולין בטהרה, chullin be-taharah, I’m going to treat my חולין chullin as
if it’s תרומה, trumah, and I’m going to be so careful with
it as careful as I would be with תרומה, trumah, and I
won’t even let say let a שני sheni touch it.
Or I’ll be so careful with my חולין chullin that I’m going
to treat it as if it’s קודש, kodesh, and I won’t even
let a שלישי shlishi touch it. So the question is if you
had adopt that practice, to what degree do we also sort of
הלכתית halachit say that now it can become טמא tamei like the
thing you’ve been treating it as? Okay, if I’m going to treat
it as תרומה, trumah, this food, normal food can’t be, can only
be a שני, sheni, not a שלישי. shlishi. If I’m going to
treat it as תרומה trumah, and try to avoid contact with a
שני, sheni, maybe then it הלכתית halachit can become טמא tamei like
תרומה trumah and it can become a שלישי. shlishi. Okay, so that’s
what he’s saying. When are we talking that you ate a שלישי?
shlishi? If it’s חולין chullin that you treated as if it was
תרומה. trumah And because you treated it as תרומה, trumah. it’s able
to become a שלישי. shlishi. You ate it, and then you become
טמא tamei vis-a-vis קודש. kodesh. Now why did he limit it to
that case? Because that we’re able to, because basically the second position
of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer does not really want you to become
טמא tamei when you eat a שלישי. shlishi. He says the basic
גזירה gezeirah is if you eat a ראשון rishon or a שני
sheni you become טמא, tamei not a שלישי. shlishi. But I will
concede that there is one case where if you eat a שלישי
shlishi you’ll be טמא. tamei, And what is that?
That’s if it’s real תרומה trumah, that became a שלישי, shlishi, maybe
no. But if it’s food that you treated as if it were
תרומה trumah that became a שלישי, shlishi, then yes. Why would we
be more strict? Because then we can’t trust that you really guarded
the food as well as you say you did, and because it’s
really only חולין, chullin, and therefore we’re going to be more
strict on what you’re trying to make as if it’s
תרומה trumah when it’s not really תרומה.
trumah I understand. And why if you eat a ראשון rishon or
שני sheni you’re a שני? sheni? I don’t understand that.
Well, meaning, what the גמרא’s Gemara upgrading the שני.
sheni. Right. So the גמרא’s Gemara going to get to it. We’re
just quoting. Come, now. So anyway, so but the point here is
about this issue. You say you’ve treated it so carefully that it’s
going to be, that it’s like תרומה trumah. and all it became
was a שלישי, shlishi, nothing else. But because it’s really חולין, chullin,
we don’t trust you treated it as carefully as you were trying
to, because at the end of the day it’s only חולין chullin
and maybe it became טמא, tamei. maybe it’s a worse טומאה, tumah,
maybe it’s a ראשון, rishon, maybe it’s a שני. sheni. So once
it became טמא tamei, and it’s only חולין, chullin, we’re going to
be concerned at a higher level. Anyway, let’s not worry so much
about the שלישי shlishi case. The basic point is is that רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is not so prepared to make you טמא tamei
by eating the שלישי, shlishi, only in a very special case. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara goes on. Now let’s understand, now that we’ve
established that it’s רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, let’s understand why. אוכל אוכל
ראשון ואוכל אוכל שני, ochel ochel rishon ve-ochel ochel sheni, מאי טעמא
גזרו בה רבנן? mai ta’ama gazru beh rabbanan? Why did they say
if you ate a ראשון rishon or a שני sheni you became
טמא, tamei טומאה? tumah? דזימנין דאכיל אוכלין טמאין, de-zimnin de-achil ochlin tme’in,
sometimes you’ll be eating טמא tamei, food, okay, like this case of
a ראשון rishon or a שני, sheni, ושקיל משקין דתרומה ושדי לפומיה,
ve-shakil mashkin de-trumah ve-shadi le-pumeh, and here you are, you’re a כהן,
kohen, so you’re eating this טמא tamei food, that’s okay, it’s not
תרומה, trumah and then but what’s also being served at the meal
is some תרומה trumah, wine. And you had totally forgotten that the
wine was תרומה trumah because the food wasn’t. So you have this
טמא tamei food in your mouth, you wash it down with a
glass of wine. You have now made the תרומה טמא terumah tamei.
in your mouth. So since what's in your mouth is a ראשון
rishon or a שני, sheni, that's enough to make
תרומה טמא. terumah tamei. So in order to avoid those cases, we
did not want you eating a ראשון rishon or שני, sheni, or
to say it the other way, if you're eating a ראשון rishon
or שני, sheni, you have to be aware that that makes you
טמא. tamei And when you become aware, like if I'm just eating
it and I'm טהור, tahor, right, I'm טהור, tahor, I'm a כהן,
kohen, here's my תרומה trumah wine, all of this is non-תרומה, trumah
my food, so I say fine, I'm טהור, tahor, this stuff isn't
going to make me טמא, tamei I can eat it, it's not
תרומה, trumah this תרומה terumah is טהור, tahor, שלום ישראל, shalom yisrael,
everything is fine, I can eat the bread, I can drink the
wine, I'm טהור, tahor, I can drink the תרומה, terumah, and as
I do, I forget that, oh, I had the bread in my
mouth and I washed it down with wine and now the wine
was תרומה terumah, and became טמא. tamei. So if you tell me
that when I eat this bread, if it's a ראשון rishon or
שני, sheni, I'm going to be a שני, sheni, then I'm going
to know I can't be eating that bread and drinking תרומה terumah
wine at the same meal and we'll avoid the cases. Yeah?
How is this different from, I ate the, I ate the טמא
tamei. bread half an hour ago, it's still in my stomach?
Yes, so in your stomach things don't become
טמא. tamei, Now תוספות tosafot actually does discuss that if that, that
there is another דרבנן drabbanan exactly about that, which is called פסול
גויה, p'sul g'viyah, the פסול p'sul of the person or whatever, which
is exactly that, which is a larger שיעור shiur and was an
earlier תקנה, takkanah, which was sort of exactly what you were saying
that if you eat a large שיעור shiur of something טמא, tamei.
so that, so at least a certain amount got into your stomach
and then you were to drink some, you know, something else, it
would become טמא tamei in your stomach, that's all a דרבנן drabbanan
because since people do think that way, it's not true, but if
we let them have טמא tamei. food in their stomach and then
bring in, you know, drink let's say some תרומה terumah, wine, they
would come to have them together outside of their stomach. But anyway
that is an earlier גזירה, gezeirah, תוספות tosafot does acknowledge that, but
this goes one that's only about eating תרומה, terumah this says we
went so far to say that you become טמא, tamei, you can't
even touch. Once you eat, this is a later and more strict
גזירה, gezeirah, even if you eat a small amount of this, you
are becoming טמא tamei and you can't touch things because of this
concern of washing it down with wine. One minute, let's keep on
reading.
Okay. So שותה משקין טמאים, shoteh mashkin t'meim, just to see the
comparison case, מאי טעמא גזרו בהו רבנן, mai ta'ama gazru behu rabbanan,
why do they say you can't drink טמא tamei liquid, or actually
you then you become טמא, tamei, why did they say that? You
become a שני sheni because of the flip case טומאה, tumah, דזימנין
דשתו משקין טמאים dizimnin deshatu mashkin t'meim because you'll be drinking this
טמא tamei wine, which is fine, it's not תרומה, terumah you're drinking
it, ושקל אוכלין דתרומה, v'shakal ochlin d'terumah, and but your bread will
be תרומה terumah bread. So again without a גזירה, gezeirah, you'll say
it's fine, the bread is תרומה, terumah, it's טהור, tahor, the wine
is טמא tamei but it's not going to make me טמא, tamei,
so I can have the bread and the wine at the same
meal. And there'll be times where you'll be drinking the wine and
then put the bread in your mouth while the wine is still
in your mouth and you'll make the תרומה terumah, טמא. tamei So
if we therefore say by drinking the wine you become טמא, tamei
you won't have it at the same meal that you're having תרומה
terumah with. Okay, ופסול לה. u-fasul lah. So the גמרא gemara says
היינו הך, hainu hach, so why is it two separate גזרות? gezeirot?
It's all the same. טמא tamei, food makes you טמא. tamei. No.
מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought שכיחי והא לא שכיחי.
sh'chichi v'ha lo sh'chichi. It's much more common to have food in
your mouth and try to wash it down with a drink than
to have drink in your mouth and put food in at the
same time. It's actually quite physically difficult to do that because as
you have the drink in your mouth and you're trying to get
the food, I mean, the drink is going down. So, so it's
much more likely that it'll be the reverse and therefore they made
one גזירה gezeirah and then they followed it through the other for
symmetry even though it's a lot less common. You had a question,
Charlie?
Do they have a שיעור shiur for how much you have to
do to make it טמא? tamei, Yes.
Yes, so let me just double check. The earlier גזירה gezeirah was
like a lot, was like two ביצים beitzim or something. Here it's,
one
minute let me.
Yeah, תוספות tosafot here assumes that it's just a כביצה. kebeitzah. Okay.
But anyway but over there but the other גזירה gezeirah was maybe
two כביצה kebeitzah or whatever, so yes, there is a minimum שיעור.
shiur. Okay. In general there's a question about a minimum שיעור shiur
needed to transfer טומאה. tumah. Okay.
So if you're eating it piece by piece, you might have thought,
and I would think, swallow the bread and then
drink the wine but not in your mouth.
Right, that would be fine if it's not in your mouth.
Yeah, yeah, that would be, well, there's again, there's an earlier גזירה
gezeirah that there's a concern about even what happens in your stomach,
but that's a larger שיעור. shiur.
But in between your stomach, I don't know where it was.
Well whatever, what happens inside your body, yeah, yeah, yeah, but דאורייתא
de'oraita it doesn't, what happens inside your body has no relevance. Okay.
So the גמרא gemara says like this, right, I mean little kids
will say that oh, the meat and the milk are mixing up
in my stomach, you know, how could I so anyway whatever. Anyway
so the גמרא gemara says like this, okay, so those two are
about food making you טמא tamei as a way to prevent having
mixing טהור tahor and טמא tamei. food, תרומה terumah, with your food.
So therefore any eating of food makes you טמא tamei? so you
won't have it at the same meal that you're having תרומה terumah
with. That's number, those are the first two גזרות. gezeirot. Then it
says like this, הבא ראשו ורובו במים שאובים, haba rosho v'rubo b'mayim
shu'uvim, מאי טעמא גזרו בהו רבנן, mai ta'ama gazru behu rabbanan, why
did they say when you immerse yourself essentially in a bath of
drawn water are you טמא tamei טומאה? tumah? אמר רב ביבי אמר
רב אסי שבתחילה היו טובלין במי מערה
מכונסין, amar rav bibi amar rav assi shebat'chilah hayu tovlin b'mei me'arah
mechunasin, originally they were dipping in cave water. And here talking primarily
about men, I mean obviously it applies to women as well, but
you know, men, כהנים, Kohanim, presumably this also has to do with
כהנים Kohanim eating תרומה. terumah It could also be about the earlier
תקנה takkanah about a בעל קרי baal keri who had to go
to the מקוה mikvah before he said שמע Shema or he davened.
So where did they go to the מקוה? mikvah? So they would
go into these these waters in the caves like these that was
gathered water, it was מכונסין. mechunasin. And they were and it was
very smelly water, you know, they would go into some type of
a natural gathering of water, would not be a beautiful pond or
a lake, it would be some type of a place where rainwater
had gathered and it's all smelly and disgusting. ועשו קבע ve'asum keva
and therefore what did they do? I'm sorry I skipped a line.
והיו נותנים עליהם מים שאובים veha'yu notnin aleihem mayim she'uvim and therefore
they wanted to clean themselves from the gunk of the מקוה mikvah
so they would take a bath afterwards. Like nowadays it's a problem
because so many people use the מקוה, mikvah, you want to take
a bath or a shower after. So now but that led to
a problem. What was the problem? התחילו ועשו קבע. hitchilu ve'asum keva.
They started making it a fixed practice. After the מקוה mikvah you
gotta take a bath. So and therefore גזרו עליהם טומאה. gazru aleihem
tumah. They said it's gonna make you טמא. tamei What does that
mean? So מאי קבע? mai keva? What does it mean that they
made it a regular practice? אמר אביי Amar Abaye שהיו אומרים shehayu
omrim לא אלו מטהרים אלא אלו ואלו מטהרים. lo elu metaharim ela
elu ve'elu metaharim. They would say it's not the מקוה mikvah that
does it, it's the מקוה mikvah plus the bath. So since they
wanted the people to to not confuse that it was the bath
that was part of the of the purification process, they said actually
if you take a bath right after going to the מקוה mikvah
you'll be טמא. tamei So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה רבא
amar lei Rava מאי נפקא מינה? mai nafka minei? הא קטבלו בהנך.
ha katavlu behanach. So which is I mean רבא Rava says, so
what, so let them think it's the מקוה mikvah plus the bath,
at least they're getting the מקוה mikvah in. Right? So big deal
they think you have to do some other practice. Of course there's
an obvious answer, first of all you don't want people to have
a misunderstanding of halachically what's the real act and so on and
you could imagine a lot of things problems it would lead to.
But רבא Rava says if it was just that I wouldn't be
bothered. אלא אמר רבא ela amar Rava שהיו אומרים shehayu omrim לא
אלו מטהרים אלא אלו מטהרים. lo elu metaharim ela elu metaharim. They
wouldn't say both, they'd say the real thing that makes you טהור
tahor is the bath after. Since anyway that was clean water. So
maybe then they'll stop doing the מקוה mikvah altogether. So therefore they
had to say that taking the bath afterwards made you טמא tamei
so that people would not people would not do that right after
the מקוה. mikvah. Now you there's a question about like how long
afterwards would that be? I mean are you never allowed to take
a bath after and every time after you've taken a bath you
have to go to the מקוה mikvah again? So you can never
really be clean? So there's an assumption in substance that רש״י Rashi
sort of says here, reads in here although it's not explicit, that
it basically means right like immediately afterwards. And then the context is
what's immediate and does it mean at the same
location, how do you exactly define immediate? But some way it's within
the context of immediately afterwards. Now interestingly this leads to a discussion
about women taking a shower or after they go to the מקוה.
mikvah. And some פוסקים poskim said yeah, women should only wait till
they get home to take a shower or if they take a
shower right away it's exactly this problem. הגר״א the Gra however says,
what are you talking about? Let them take a shower. So what's
the result of taking a shower? They didn't say it was אסור
assur to take a shower. They said if you take a shower
or bath right after the מקוה mikvah you become שני לטומאה. sheni
letumah. Right? So ישתבח, yishtabach, you're שני לטומאה, sheni letumah, we're all
טמאי מת tamei meis anyway. It's not the נדה niddah problem, right?
The נדה niddah problem was solved by going to the מקוה mikvah
and now you took a shower, fine, we're all much more טמא
tamei. than this שני לטומאה. sheni letumah. So there's no איסור issur
to do it, it's just that it makes you this low-level טומאה
tumah which is relevant in a world where טומאה tumah is is
an issue. Okay so that is this that is this תקנה takkanah
that the shower after the מקוה mikvah or bath after the מקוה
mikvah makes you טמא. tamei. Yes.
How about the second part about the woman taking a shower, how
does it make it שני לטומאה? sheni letumah?
Because that's the תקנה takkanah that taking a bath or shower immediately
after the מקוה mikvah makes you immediately after.
But is it a custom right I mean I'm just a I
don't know of that after going to the מקוה mikvah you should
wait like three hours or something before showering or you really?
I'm not familiar with it but I assume it's based on this,
I assume I assume it's based on this. But the point is
is that is that it's really silly, certainly in the in the
case for women it's silly. If you're going to the מקוה mikvah
anyway, men going to the מקוה mikvah if it's for בעל קרי
baal keri then it's silly it's not relevant to the בעל קרי
baal keri issue. If it's like before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and
יום כיפור Yom Kippur where you want to be totally טהור, tahor,
then you could say okay I want to be totally טהור tahor
but even so you're not totally טהור tahor because we're assuming we're
all טמאי מת. tamei meis. The מקוה mikvah didn't help for טמאי
מת tamei meis you know so all the only result of this
is not that it is that it makes you a שני לטומאה.
sheni letumah. So a very or generic שני לטומאה. sheni letumah.
So these are so that's now my exact question. We go to
the מקוה mikvah especially for ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור
Yom Kippur so is there a problem taking a shower afterwards or
is there not?
I don't think so. I mean David says here there's some מנהג,
minhag, I I can't I I don't think so. Yeah.
What about going to a lake, ocean? Didn't people do that when
they when they didn't have a מקוה? mikvah?
Yeah, yeah. What about today? Yeah, right.
It's not like a cave.
Right, right, right. But here apparently the most convenient places at least
in the חמת גדר? Hamat Gader? No? What? Yeah but it's natural
water. Natural water is fine or rain collected rainwater is fine.
But did you say it was a problem if it was like
the the
frost because then you're saying yeah there's some times and there's too
much there's too much rainwater in the in the lake but whatever
as a general rule it's fine. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. Okay so.
Yes,
yes, from where? Yeah. It says, well, it says ורחץ את כל
בשרו במים, Verachatz et kol besaro bamayim, which literally means wash your...
but there's a... but it also says מקוה מים יהיה טהור. Mikve
mayim yihye tahor. So from different places in ויקרא, Vayikra, it's... it's
not explicit in all kinds. Like the interesting thing is, it's not
explicit by נדה, niddah,
the going to the מקוה mikveh is not mentioned explicitly. Right. So
the... it gets discussed. Anyway, וטהור שנפלו ראשו ורובו שלשה לוגין מים
שאובין, vethahor shenafalu rosho verubbo sheloshah lugin mayim she'uvin,
and if a טהור tahor person basically took a shower... now here
it says וטהור. vethahor. See why would it say הבא בראשו ורובו?
habba berosho verubbo? And here it says וטהור, vethahor, a טהור tahor
person. So the point here is, is... no, the point here is
that the one before was a guy who a minute ago had
been טמא, tamei who was immediately in the context of going to
the מקוה. mikveh. Here we're saying there was one גזירה, gezeirah, if
you go to the bath right after going to the מקוה. mikveh.
There's another גזירה, gezeirah, you didn't go to the מקוה. mikveh. You've
just been טהור tahor for the last week and you took a
shower. So there also you're טמא, tamei even not in the context
of having just gone to the מקוה. mikveh. So why is that?
So מאי טעמא גזרו בהו רבנן טומאה, mai ta'ama gazru behu rabanan
tum'ah, דלא הא לא קיימא הא. delo ha lo kayma ha. Because
if we wouldn't say you're טמא tamei. by taking a shower סתם,
stam, then nobody would believe us when we would say you're טמא
tamei, by taking a bath after the מקוה. mikveh. So once we
had to say you want to be טמא tamei, by taking a
bath after the מקוה, mikveh, we had to sort of generalize it
a little bit more and say in general, if you immerse yourself
or take a... or take a shower in drawn water, that makes
you טמא. tamei Of course, you've got to imagine, I mean I
have no idea what the implications about this were, but you know
on the one hand, we're always talking every minute about going to
the bathhouse, right? It was obviously a very common phenomenon.
And ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, the Romans brought a lot of much
more, you know, bodily hygiene, you know, with all their... with all
their bathhouse practices and so on. But if people are being מקפיד
makpid about eating בטהרה, betaharah, so...
so every time you take a shower or a bath, you've got
to go to the מקוה mikveh again or whatever. How... how clean
can you stay? Now, maybe again, the point is that you're only
a שני sheni and therefore it's only relevant for תרומה. terumah So...
so okay, but at least for the כהנים, kohanim, how clean could
they stay once you had these גזירות? gezeirot? I don't really know.
Maybe you have to do like a... like a body wash, like
one limb at a time so you're not doing the whole... but
I really don't know the implications about this for cleanliness. Anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. וספר, Vesefer, now ספרי קדש, Sifrei
Kodesh, it might mean... it certainly means at least a ספר תורה,
Sefer Torah, presumably it means all ספרי קדש, Sifrei Kodesh, as we'll
see as the גמרא Gemara continues. מאי טעמא גזרו בהו רבנן טומאה?
mai ta'ama gazru behu rabanan tum'ah? Why did they say it's טמא?
tamei It's quite an amazing thing that the holiest thing, a ספר...
sefer a ספר תורה Sefer Torah. is טמא. tamei Now, to some
degree you can understand this because you know... that although טומאה tum'ah
often is the exact antithesis of קדושה, kedushah, but both of them
are sort of like this metaphysical status that's around something and that's
about sort of distancing yourself from something. So you can understand that
in a world where טומאה tum'ah was much more of a... of
a lived reality
than, you know, than let's say the קדושה kedushah of a ספר
תורה. Sefer Torah, Meaning what happens? If I touch a ספר תורה,
sefer Torah that actually has... changes my metaphysical state, and now I
can't eat תרומה. terumah So it turns it into a lived metaphysical
reality other than just saying, "Oh, it's קדושת ספר תורה." kedushat Sefer
Torah. So in a way, the גמרא Gemara will give the reason
it gives, but I think that in a way, although טומאה tum'ah
and קדושה kedushah are antithetical, there's a sense in which you sort
of understand that it creates certain realities around it and that was
certainly experienced in the level... in the world of טומאה וטהרה. tum'ah
vetaharah. Yes.
This would seem to be support for Rambam's idea that the purpose
for the טומאה וטהרה tum'ah vetaharah laws is in fact to create
more reverence for sacred things, that we can't be just around them
constantly.
Right, that's a good point, but there it's because of טומאה tum'ah
being as an antithesis to טהרה taharah and to keep your distance.
Here it's the exact... the thing creates the טומאה, tum'ah, so it
does start to confuse the boundaries a little bit. Let's see what
the גמרא Gemara explains what the reason is.
אמר רב מששרשיא שבתחילה היו מצניעין את האוכלין דתרומה אצל ספר תורה.
Amar Rav Mesharshaya shebetchillah hayu matzni'in et ha'ochlin detherumah etzel Sefer Torah.
Originally they would store תרומה Terumah. with ספרי תורה. Sifrei Torah. Why?
ואמרו האי קודש והאי קודש, Ve'amru hai kodesh vehai kodesh, they're both
holy, let's store them together. Okay, what's the problem? וכיון דחזו דקאתו
לידי פסידא, Ukeivan dechazu dek'athu lidei psida, but they saw that it
was starting to lead to loss. Why? Because the rats would go
to the... to the תרומה terumah. and then they'd start eating away
at the ספרי תורה. Sifrei Torah. So גזרו בהו רבנן טומאה, gazru
behu rabanan tum'ah, they treated it as טמא. tamei. Okay,
וידיים, Veyadayim, מפני שהידיים עסקניות הן. mipnei shehayadayim askaniyot hen. Hands are
always a שני, sheni, even if you've gone to the מקוה, mikveh,
you always assume that your hands are a שני sheni and you
have to wash your hands before eating תרומה terumah. because hands are
very busy. You never know where your hands have been, they're always
scratching parts of your body, touching things, play... you know, you'll be
playing with something and you don't even realize you're playing with it
in your hand. So therefore we're always concerned that your hand might
have touched something טמא tamei? and a hand will always be a
שני. sheni.
So we see here הספר, Hasefer, that means it's not... we wouldn't
apply it to תפילין, tefillin, we wouldn't apply it to like... ספרי
קדש? Sifrei Kodesh?
So תוספות Tosafot says, so... so... yeah. So it's not so... it's
not... right, the גמרא, Gemara, but since the גמרא Gemara gives the
reason, I mean it did say אוכלין אצל ספר תורה. ochlin etzel
Sefer Torah. Anyway, it does start to... It is unclear whether ספר
sefer is limited to ספר תורה sefer Torah. or general ספרי קודש.
sifrei kodesh. The assumption this is here it's unclear but in מסכת
ידיים Masechet Yadayim it's very clear because in מסכת ידיים Masechet Yadayim
I should have mentioned this anyway because we talked about canonizing the
book of יחזקאל. Yechezkel. The way the גמרא Gemara discusses what was
in the canon and not in the canon was whether it's מטמא
את הידיים. metamei et hayadayim. So for example there is a debate
is שיר השירים Shir Hashirim מטמא את הידיים, metamei et hayadayim, which
is a way of saying is שיר השירים Shir Hashirim in the
canon or not? Maybe it's just love poetry. And then רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva said חס ושלום לעולם לא היתה מחלוקת בשיר השירים שכל
השירים קודש ושיר השירים קודש קודשים, chas v'shalom l'olam lo haytah machloket
be-Shir Hashirim she-kol hashirim kodesh v'Shir Hashirim kodesh kodashim, right? שיר השירים
Shir Hashirim is the holiest of holies, it's very you know in
terms of its sort of mystical significance. But anyway whenever there's a
debate or discussion about what things were in the canon or not
the way it's articulated is: is it מטמא את הידיים? metamei et
hayadayim? Okay so but there is a slight difference because as we're
going to see in a minute let's read the next line. Okay
so because that specifically את הידיים, et hayadayim, let's read the next
line. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: והידיים מפני שהידיים עסקניות.
ve-hayadayim mipnei she-hayadayim askaniyot. Okay תנא, tana, we taught in the ברייתא:
braita: אף ידיים הבאות מחמת ספר פוסלות את התרומה. af yadayim haba'ot
machmat sefer poslot et ha-Terumah. If you touch a ספר sefer, your
ידיים yadayim also become a שני. sheini. Now who cares? Because I
mean your hands are always a שני. sheini. So let's say though
you immediately went to the מקווה mikveh and you kept you were
looking at your hands you kept your eye on your hands as
it were and they didn't touch anything and then you handled a
ספר תורה. sefer Torah. Then your hands would also be a שני
sheini by handling a ספר תורה. sefer Torah Why? Let's take a
look. משום
דפרנא, mishum d'Parna, there is the word פרנסא, parnasa, דאמר רב פרנך
אמר רבי יוחנן האוחז ספר תורה ערום נקבר ערום. d'amar Rav Parnach
amar Rabbi Yochanan ha-ocheiz sefer Torah arom nikvar arom. If you hold
a ספר תורה sefer Torah naked, meaning if you directly touch the
קלף klaf of a ספר תורה sefer Torah and not not like
you know holding it by the by the you know mantle or
whatever then you will be buried naked. So the גמרא Gemara says:
ערום סלקא דעתך? arom salka daitach? Literally buried naked? Why you mean
you don't put תכריכים tachrichim on the person? אלא אמר רבי זירא
ערום בלא מצוה. ela amar Rabbi Zeira arom belo mitzvah. It means
you'll be naked of מצוות mitzvot when you're buried. So the גמרא
Gemara says: בלא מצוה סלקא דעתך? belo mitzvah salka daitach? Really you
would go that far just because of this one sin you'd be
stripped of all your מצוות? mitzvot? אלא אימא ערום בלא אותה מצוה.
ela eima arom belo otah mitzvah. You don't get that מצוה mitzvah
that you have got like so if you were handling it when
you had הגבהה hagbah or גלילה gelilah or you had an עליה
aliyah or you were learning from it so to say and in
that thing that you were doing with it you were handling the
קלף klaf directly then you lose the שכר sechar for that מצוה.
mitzvah. So that is a sense of the real קדושה kedusha of
the תורה Torah about not handling it directly you always handle it
like why we use a יד yad and all these types of
things. And because they didn't want people to handle it directly the
consequence of touching it directly was that your hands become טמא. tamei.
Okay so that's ספרי קודש מטמאים את הידיים. sifrei kodesh metameim et
hayadayim. Why would you want to handle it directly?
Because it wasn't considered I mean again how do you express reverence
and קדושה kedusha to an inanimate object? So I mean one of
the ways we do it is like we kiss
it. That's a good point but I think
there's...
everyone's touching it
it's
going to degrade the quality.
But besides the practical issue of degrading look there's no way of
addressing the סופר, sofer, I'll have to see it's interesting how that
gets discussed but presumably there there's no option. But the point is
if the way one of the ways we express that something is
holy is that we're very reluctant to handle it and to touch
it, up you know sometimes it's because it's fragile, don't touch that
painting don't touch that thing or whatever but you know if something
is very special you very much want to protect how it's touched
and handled. So I totally understand that.
Yes fine so study without directly handling the קלף. klaf. You roll
it up this way you do it through a you take a
טלית tallis when we have to like adjust something you're doing גלילה
gelilah and it's you know you take a טלית tallis and you
through
the טלית tallis
you move it it's just you don't directly touch it with your
hands.
Yeah yeah it's just directly touching it with your hands.
Yeah yeah it's touching the קלף klaf directly with your hands. I
see it makes a lot of sense about how we experience the
holiness but you
kind of building up all these rituals in order to increase its
specialness.
Yes right but doesn't mean that you can't use it just you
know use it in a particular way.
Almost an idolatrous object.
I don't think so, I don't think so. There's a way I
mean look you know the רמב"ם Rambam was concerned like you said
that these things become talismans and you know idolatrous and so on.
But on the other hand you there's a there's a middle ground
where it has קדושה kedusha where it's not... yeah but I don't
see this as going too far. I mean even the strength of
your buried ערום arom you know naked the גמרא Gemara really sort
of minimized that. So now I just would want to say something
about this so this is where it's clearly is talking about like
all ספרי קודש sifrei kodesh because this is מטמאים את הידיים metameim
et hayadayim and here that's and תוספות Tosafot sort of points it
out. If you take a look at תוספות Tosafot האוחז ספר תורה
ערום וצ"ע דמאי שנא ספר תורה דהוא הדין שאר ספרי קודש דנמי
מטמאי את הידיים. ha-ocheiz sefer Torah arom v'tzarich iyun d'mai shena sefer
Torah de-hu hadin shear sifrei kodesh denami metamei et hayadayim.
So that's as I said the well that you're not handling... That's
what I said that the way you determine the discussion of if
something is in the canon or not is if it's מטמא את
הידיים. mitamei es hayadayim. Was it in this category? But that's not
the earlier גזירה, gezeirah, the earlier גזירה gezeirah was not if you
touch it your hands become שני, sheni, that's if the ספר תורה
sefer Torah, directly touches תרומה, terumah it makes the תרומה terumah טמא.
tamei. Your hands didn't touch it, it just directly touched תרומה. terumah
Okay, so that maybe is limited to just a ספר תורה, sefer
Torah but again, it makes sense to think that it's by all
ספרים. sefarim. Yes, make one out
of silver as well? Yes. I mean well that was the question
whether you use it as מטמא את הידיים, mitamei es hayadayim, whether
he used touch parts of his hands.
They say elsewhere a ספר תורה sefer Torah? cannot become טמא. tamei
That's why women can touch it because fire then...
well, okay, so that's an interesting right. That's an interesting question which
I've discussed with others but I don't want to enter into right
now. The גמרא Gemara says אין דברי תורה מקבלין טומאה. ein divrei
Torah mekabelin tumah. But does that mean the actual scroll itself cannot
become a מקבל טומאה? mekabel tumah? But does that mean the actual
scroll cannot become טמא? tamei. It doesn't seem that way. The רמב"ם
Rambam when he brings down does not talk about ספרי תורה sifrei
Torah but let's say a מת meis touched a scroll I was
using for some other book. So it's like a כלי, kli, it
can become טמא. tamei. So is there some special exclusion by the
ספר תורה? sefer Torah It's not אין ספרי תורה מקבלין טומאה, ein
sifrei Torah mekabelin tumah, it's אין תורה מקבלת טומאה. ein Torah mekabeles
tumah.
But רמב"ם Rambam says women who are
נדה niddah can touch a תורה Torah so he's...
I understand, but that's...
there's no prohibition of it becoming טמא, tamei? let's put it that
way. There's no prohibition of it becoming טמא. tamei. Not like תרומה.
terumah, But what about...
on a ספר תורה sefer Torah, when the holy, you know, when
the holy temple was being destroyed and... pork was, pigs or
whatever, if any of that stuff touched the ספר תורה, sefer Torah
which I'm sure it did, now what is the status of it?
Right, so yeah, so this is the point, it doesn't lose its
status. Look, every time we handle it, we make it טמא tamei,
because we're טמאי מת tamei meis and we touch it. So to
the point is it doesn't lose its status and there's no prohibition
of it becoming טמא. tamei. Okay, but I don't think it's a
foregone conclusion that it itself does not become טמא. tamei But it
doesn't affect its holiness.
People are handling these or putting it in a locker.
Fine.
All right. So
yeah, all right, that's, yeah, but that's not a whole ספר, sefer
so that's a good question. I'll have to get back to that.
All right, let's go on.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. האי גזרו ברישא,
hai gazru bereisha, which did they say first? אילימא האי גזרו ברישא,
eileima hai gazru bereisha, first they said first that a ספר sefer
becomes טמא. tamei. So,
כיון דהך גזרו ברישא, keivan dehach gazru bereisha, I'm sorry, which of
the two, meaning was it that
the handling the ספרי קודש sifrei kodesh or was it that the
ספר תורה sefer Torah, itself becomes טמא? tamei. One minute.
No, no, no, I got it mixed up. Was it first that
your hands are טמא, tamei. סתם stam hands are טמא, tamei? or
hands that touch a ספר sefer are טמא? tamei, So אילימא הך
גזרו ברישא, eileima hach gazru bereisha, first they said all hands are
טמא, tamei, so כיון דהך גזרו ברישא, keivan dehach gazru bereisha, since
they said all hands are טמא, tamei? הך למה לי? hach lamah
li? Why would you have to say when your hands touch a
ספר sefer they're טמא? tamei, Right? You've already said hands are always
טמא. tamei, אלא הך גזרו ברישא, ela hach gazru bereisha, first they
said when your hands touch a ספר sefer they're טמא. tamei? והדר
גזרו בכולהו ידיים, vehadar gazru bechulhu yadayim, and then they say, you
know what, hands all the time are טמא. tamei. Now there's still
a נפקא מינה nafka mina if you go to the מקוה mikvah
and immediately you touch a ספר תורה, sefer Torah. so then your
hands would be טמא tamei. and they wouldn't have otherwise because you
had not lost focus on your hands. But basically the point is
once we say hands are טמא, tamei. there's no real need for
saying if you handle a ספר sefer your hands are טמא, tamei
that was taken for granted. Okay, but there are two separate גזירות,
gezeiros, one is if you handle it your hands become טמא tamei,
and the other is the ספר sefer, itself is מטמא. mitamei. And
again, presumably it applies to other ספרים, sefarim, but the גמרא Gemara
does focus on the ספר תורה. sefer Torah, Like a lot of
good points raised here about like a סופר sofer writing a ספר
תורה, sefer Torah. fixing a ספר תורה. Michael speaks about when you
put the מזוזה mezuzah in the, you know, in the box or
whatever, those types of things. So that's not a question of טומאה,
tumah, that's what constitutes this idea of האוחז ערום מצווה ערום. ha'ocheiz
arom mitzvah arom. So that might be a smaller scope than these
טומאה tumah issues and maybe even טומאה tumah is different if it's
not the whole ספר, if it's just a פרשה. parsha. So I'd
have to get back to that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues.
Okay, וטבול יום, ve'tevul yom, a טבול יום tevul yom is a
שני sheni and makes תרומה terumah. טמא. tamei, טבול יום דאורייתא! tevul
yom d'Oraisa! What do you mean count it in the eighteen things?
It's biblical! דכתיב ובא השמש וטהר. dechsiv uva hashemesh vetaher. Somebody is
טמא, tamei he goes to the מקוה, mikvah, he's טהור, tahor, but
but he's טהור tahor only when the sun sets. He's only fully
טהור tahor then, and until the sun sets he's a שני sheni
and he makes תרומה terumah. טמא. tamei, פסוק! pasuk! So סמי מכאן
טבול יום, sami mikan tevul yom, fine, don't include it in the
list. Meaning the משנה Mishnah was not listing the eighteen things. This
list of things that you're a שני sheni was in a משנה
Mishnah in זבים, Zavim, which is just a list of things that's
a שני. sheni. We're saying that that was the eighteen things. So
saying yes, it's in the list of things that you're a שני,
sheni, but it's not part of the
eighteen תקנות takanos of שמאי והלל. Shammai veHillel. Okay.
It's still there though, nobody removed it.
No, but that's my
point, they're not editing the משנה. Mishnah. They're
not saying
right, סמי מכאן sami mikan תוספות Tosafos points out explicitly, לא מן
המשנה. lo min haMishnah. that whole list of things that are שני,
sheni, that's from the eighteen things of שמאי Shammai and הלל. Hillel.
So now what we're saying is we don't mean the whole list,
one of those things is דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, but everything else in that
list is from the things of שמאי Shammai and הלל. Hillel. Okay,
yes.
Is רב חסדא Rav Chisda and and these rabbis, they are confirming
what the list of הלל Hillel and שמאי... Shammai...
They're identifying what the list... Right, identifying. Right, the משנה Mishnah just
says there these are some from the eighteen things, some of the
stuff we talked about before, and now we're trying to create the
complete list. So we've identified this משנה Mishnah about things that make
you a שני, sheni, and we're saying most of that משנה Mishnah
is from the eighteen things of שמאי Shammai and הלל. Hillel. Okay,
so we're trying to clarify what were the eighteen things. Now, going
through that משנה, Mishnah, continuing that משנה: Mishnah: והאוכלין שנטמאו במשקין, Ve-ha-ochlin
she-nitmu be-mashkin,
so food that became טמא tamei through liquid, the food is considered
a שני sheni and makes תרומה terumah טמא. tamei. So the גמרא
Gemara says, במשקין דמאי, be-mashkin de-mai, what type of liquid? אילימא במשקין
הבאים מחמת שרץ, Ileima be-mashkin ha-ba'im machmat sheretz, it's liquid that touched
a שרץ, sheretz, which is a טמא, tamei, which is an אב,
av, so the שרץ sheretz is an אב, av, the liquid is
a ראשון, rishon, it makes the food into a שני. sheni. So
that you don't need a special דרבנן de-rabbanan for that, that's the
basic way טומאה tumah works. So the גמרא Gemara says, דאורייתא נינהו,
d'Oraisa ninhu, that works biblically. Right? You got the the source is
the שרץ, sheretz, the liquid is a ראשון, rishon, and the food
is a שני. sheni. דכתיב וכל משקה אשר ישתה, De-chtiv ve-chol mashke
asher yishateh,
any liquid that's in the vessel shall become טמא. tamei. Now that's
talking about liquid becoming a שני, sheni, but nevertheless it basically says
that liquid that once liquid becomes טמא, tamei, it goes down one
level and therefore if if the שרץ sheretz is an אב, av,
the liquid is a ראשון, rishon, and it makes the food a
שני. sheni. אלא במשקין הבאים מחמת ידים. Ella be-mashkin ha-ba'im machmat yadayim.
Your hands touch liquid. Now we said your hands were a שני.
sheni. So if your hands are a שני, sheni, they really should
only be able to impact תרומה. terumah. But they touched liquid, liquid
of חולין. chullin. It should do nothing. So, and nevertheless, the גזירה
משום משקין הבאים מחמת שרץ. gezeirah mishum mashkin ha-ba'im machmat sheretz. We
said once your hands touch liquid, they turn the liquid into not
only the normal הלכה halacha would have been the liquid is nothing.
We say your hands that are a שני sheni touch liquid, not
only is it nothing, not only is it a שני, sheni, it's
a ראשון. rishon. It gets upgraded. And this is basically תוספות Tosafot
identifies this with the general principle that כל הפוסל את התרומה מטמא
את המשקין להיות תחילה. kol ha-posel es ha-terumah metamei es ha-mashkin lihyos
techilah. Anytime you have a שני sheni or higher that touches liquid,
it automatically gets upgraded and becomes a ראשון. rishon. And therefore since
your hands which are a שני sheni touch this liquid, the liquid's
a ראשון, rishon, the liquid now touches food, the food is a
שני. sheni. Okay, now why were we so much more מחמיר machmir
about liquid than about other things?
So רש"י Rashi says let me just double check the רש"י Rashi
he says yeah, he says because food doesn't always become טמא. tamei.
Food needs הכשר, hechsher, food needs to come in contact with liquid,
if you remember, food is not able to become טמא tamei until
after it's come in contact with liquid. So liquid becomes טמא tamei
more easily than food and also liquid is important is the means
in which food becomes טמא. tamei. So therefore we were much more
strict with liquid. We're going to see in another way that sometimes
liquids are even an אב הטומאה, av ha-tumah, like the spit of
a זב. zav. So the general point was, was that liquid is
easier to become טמא, tamei, it's sometimes a source of a טומאה,
tumah, we were very strict with liquid. So anytime a שני sheni
touches liquid, it becomes a ראשון. rishon. And that was this גזירה.
gezeirah. So your hands touch the liquid, they become a ראשון, rishon,
the liquid touch the food, the food is a שני. sheni. Okay,
so now it says like this: משום משקין הבאים מחמת שרץ. Mishum
mashkin ha-ba'im machmat sheretz. והכלים שנטמאו במשקין, Ve-ha-kelim she-nitmu be-mashkin,
and if vessels becomes טמא tamei in liquids. Now a vessel can
only be a ראשון. rishon. So if the vessel is becoming טמא
tamei through liquid, that means we have to consider the liquid an
אב. av. Right, the basic principle is that people and vessels can
only be a ראשון. rishon. The only thing that can be a
שני sheni and lower is food. So if we're saying that a
that liquid can make a vessel טמא, tamei, so the vessel's being
טמא, tamei, it's an אב av it's a ראשון. rishon. So that
means the liquid, we're having to treat like an אב. av. So
what type of a liquid are we treating like an אב הטומאה?
av ha-tumah? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: במשקין דמאי. Be-mashkin de-mai. אילימא במשקין דזב, Ileima be-mashkin de-zav, the
fluids of a זב zav or a זבה zavah or a נדה,
niddah, meaning a person that has, you know, per that is טמא
tamei in their person, in their body. דאורייתא נינהו, d'Oraisa ninhu, that's
biblical. דכתיב וכי ירק הזב בטהור, De-chtiv ve-chi yarok ha-zav ba-tahor, when
a זב zav spits on a טהור tahor person, he has to
go to the מקוה. mikvah. ומה שביד טהור, U-mah she-be-yad tahor, רש"י
Rashi says it's actually תמהתי לך, tameisi lecha, רש"י Rashi says that's
parenthetical, because we also use it to say even if it doesn't
hit directly the טהור tahor person, if it hits something he's carrying,
it also makes him טמא tamei because of carrying. But the basic
point is the Torah says that if the liquid the spit of
a זב zav hits a person, a person is טמא. tamei. Again,
a person can only be a ראשון, rishon, means the spit of
the זב zav is treated like an אב. av. So the same
way a זב zav is an אב, av, the spit and other
fluids of a זב, zav, of a נדה, niddah, of a זבה
zavah are an אב הטומאה. av ha-tumah. Okay, this is a principle
we've seen before. So the only liquid that can make a person
or vessel טמא tamei is the fluids of a זב. zav. So
therefore, אלא במשקין... Ella be-mashkin...
so what are we talking about? So if it's those fluids דאורייתא,
d'oraisa, it's דאורייתא. d'oraisa. אלא במאי עסקינן? ella bamai askinan? So what
are we talking about? So if it's those fluids דאורייתא, d'oraisa, it's
דאורייתא. d'oraisa. אלא במאי עסקינן במים מחמת שרץ. ella bamai askinan b'mayim
machmat sheretz. Fine, it's
what's the דרבנן. d'rabbanan. It's not the דאורייתא d'oraisa fluids of a
זב. zav. It's food that touched and liquids that touched an אב
הטומאה av hatumah like a שרץ. sheretz. גזירה משום משקי דזב. gezeirah
mishum mashke de'zav.
And the reason we were strict is because there are some liquids
that are an אב av like the liquids of a זב. zav.
So what we mean is, so what, yeah, so what we mean
is the following: there are two גזירות. gezeiros. One is if a
ראשון rishon or שני sheini touches a liquid, it becomes, the liquid
becomes a ראשון. rishon. Okay? And then it could make food טמא.
tamei. That's upgrade number one. So if you're in coach or business,
you're upgraded to, I don't know, first class.
Okay? A שני sheini or ראשון rishon touches the משקים, mashkim, they
become a ראשון. rishon. If an אב av touches the liquids, then
it becomes an אב. av. So basically שני sheini or ראשון rishon
become a ראשון, rishon, an אב av touches it, it becomes an
אב. av. Why? Because there are some liquids that are an אב
av like the liquids of a זב zav and their fluids of
a זב. zav. And therefore we're going to be מחמיר machmir that
if it touched an אב, av, it becomes an אב. av. If
it touched a ראשון rishon or שני, sheini, it becomes a ראשון.
rishon. Okay, let's read one more.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: גזירה, gezeirah,
now the גמרא Gemara starts asking a historical question, let's just read
a few more lines. ועדיין, v'adayin, when we say hands are טמא,
tamei, תלמידי שמאי והלל גזרו? tamidei Shammai v'Hillel gazru? Are you telling
me it was the students of שמאי והלל? Shammai v'Hillel? שמאי והלל
גזרו. Shammai v'Hillel gazru. שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel themselves made the
גזירה gezeirah about the hands.
דתניא: de'tanya: יוסי בן יועזר איש צרידה ויוסי בן יוחנן איש ירושלים,
Yosi ben Yoezer ish Tzeredah v'Yosi ben Yochanan ish Yerushalayim, remember them
from פרקי אבות? Pirkei Avos? Okay, גזרו טומאה על ארץ העמים. gazru
tumah al eretz ha'amim. They said that land outside of Israel is
considered טמא. tamei. We don't know where people are buried, you might
and, you know, non-Jews are not so, you know, maybe bury people
in random places, so you have to treat the land outside of
Israel as טמא, tamei, which had a very severe implication about leaving
Israel. Number one. ועל כלי זכוכית, v'al klei zechochis, and metal and
glassware is טמא, tamei, because biblically glass cannot become טמא. tamei. That's
what they did. שמעון בן שטח, Shimon ben Shatach, שמעון בן שטח
תיקן כתובה לאשה. Shimon ben Shatach tikein kesuvah l'isha. He made the
תקנה takkanah of כתובה. kesuvah. This is discussed in כתובות, Ketubot, that
originally they would put the money for women's כתובה kesuvah in escrow.
He said that's not the way to do it. If you have
the money in escrow, it's not going to be a, it's not
going to stop the husband from callously and casually divorcing his wife.
There has to be a, so what we're going to do is
we're going to have a כתובה kesuvah which means that the, that
it's an outstanding debt and if you divorce your wife, now you
have to liquidate your assets in order to pay the כתובה. kesuvah.
And that's a much more effective deterrent of a speedy divorce than
having taken the money upfront and putting it in escrow. So not
the whole institution of כתובה, kesuvah, but the idea that כתובה kesuvah
would work as an outstanding debt, that was שמעון בן שטח. Shimon
ben Shatach. וגזר טומאה על כלי מתכות, v'gazar tumah al klei matachos,
and he said metal vessels are טמא. tamei. Now metal vessels of
course can become טמא, tamei, so we'll see what that means in
the גמרא. Gemara. Anyway, and now to our point: שמאי והלל גזרו
טומאה על הידיים. Shammai v'Hillel gazru tumah al hayadayim. And it was
שמאי Shammai and הלל Hillel that said the hands. So how do
you reconcile? וכי תימא v'chi teima their students. וכי תימא שמאי וסיעתו
הלל וסיעתו? v'chi teima Shammai v'si'aso Hillel v'si'aso? You'll say no, maybe
when we said שמאי Shammai and הלל, Hillel, we meant שמאי Shammai
and his colleagues and his ישיבה, yeshiva, and הלל Hillel and his
ישיבה yeshiva and his colleagues. So it was שמאי ובית שמאי הלל
ובית הלל. Shammai v'Beis Shammai Hillel v'Beis Hillel. No. ואמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל י"ח דבר גזרו ובי"ח נחלקו. v'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel
shmoneh asar davar gazru u'be-shmoneh asar nechelku. There were eighteen things
that they, that they did, were eighteen things that they originally had
debated on, and at this one time שמאי Shammai outruled הלל. Hillel.
So the eighteen things are, are בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. The eighteen
things are things that were a matter of debate. And why is
that relevant?
ואילו הלל ושמאי לא נחלקו,
v'ilu Hillel v'Shammai
lo nechelku, right? Yeah, meaning they originally were eighteen things they debated,
and then they were, and then שמאי Shammai won out. ואילו הלל
ושמאי לא נחלקו אלא בג' מקומות. v'ilu Hillel v'Shammai lo nechelku ela
b'gimel mekomos. But הלל Hillel and שמאי Shammai only debated three things,
and these weren't among them. דאמר רב הונא בג' מקומות נחלקו ותו
לא. d'amar Rav Huna b'gimel mekomos nechelku v'sulo. Okay, so we will
end there, we will find the answer tomorrow, but here Dr. Reif
asks the question, we're saying תלמידי שמאי והלל tamidei Shammai v'Hillel did
it, we have a ברייתא braisa that says הלל ושמאי Hillel v'Shammai
did it. We can't try to say הלל ושמאי Hillel v'Shammai means
תלמידי הלל ושמאי tamidei Hillel v'Shammai and so on because we believe,
and we'll discuss more about this
tomorrow, it should be interesting, the eighteen things that were, that were,
that were
determined by הלל ושמאי Hillel v'Shammai had originally been matters of debate.
And we know that the issue of ידיים yadayim was never a
matter of debate between הלל ושמאי Hillel v'Shammai themselves. So therefore that
cannot be one of the eighteen things. So how is it that
הלל ושמאי Hillel v'Shammai earlier had already agreed on ידיים, yadayim, and
then we're finding that later their houses debated about ידיים yadayim and
finally it became one of the eighteen things? So we will find
out the answer for that tomorrow.